<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Incident Management on DFIR Delight</title><link>https://dfir-delight.de/tags/incident-management/</link><description>Recent content in Incident Management on DFIR Delight</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 05 Apr 2025 15:30:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://dfir-delight.de/tags/incident-management/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The Heart of every Incident: Incident Coordination</title><link>https://dfir-delight.de/p/incident-coordination/</link><pubDate>Sat, 05 Apr 2025 15:30:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://dfir-delight.de/p/incident-coordination/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://dfir-delight.de/p/incident-coordination/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post The Heart of every Incident: Incident Coordination" />&lt;h1 id="introduction">Introduction
&lt;/h1>&lt;p>Surprised? Let me guess—you thought forensics was the heart of every incident response. While forensics is a crucial part of Incident response, it is definitely not its heart. The following article makes it clear why.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Too often, I’m thrown into an ongoing incident where an &amp;ldquo;Incident Response Provider&amp;rdquo; is already involved. So why would the customer bring in a second incident response provider if one is already on board?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The first thing I do, when I get thrown in such an incident, is test the waters with a few simple questions:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>What are the ongoing tasks and who is responsible for them?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Where is the current situational overview, and who is updating it?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Are there established working streams?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Where are the results of the different working streams documented?&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>When I’m met with blank stares, I immediately know what’s happening: the so-called &amp;ldquo;Incident Response Provider&amp;rdquo; is just another forensics provider. They are selling forensic analysis as incident response while neglecting the most critical part—incident coordination.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Before diving into what incident coordination entails, let’s first discuss the fundamental building blocks of incident response.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="the-building-blocks-of-incident-response">The Building Blocks of Incident Response
&lt;/h1>&lt;p>Every incident response effort consists of several key building blocks, also often called working streams. Basically teams working a specific part of the IR assessment:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Incident Coordination&lt;/strong>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The glue that holds everything together, ensuring all aspects of the response function smoothly. That&amp;rsquo;s why I called in the heart of every incident.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Assigning responsibilities&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Assigning and tracking tasks&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Keeping all teams aligned&lt;/li>
&lt;li>More details in the next section&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Digital forensics&lt;/strong>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Evidence Acquisition&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Performing forensic analysis&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Assessing the extent of the attack&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Identifying attacker tactics, techniques, and procedures (TTPs) and indicators of compromise (IOCs)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Determining the impact of the attack&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Monitoring and Threat Hunting&lt;/strong>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Watching for new attacker activity using TTPs and IOCs from forensics&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Proactively hunting for additional compromised assets (systems, identities, etc.)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Remediation&lt;/strong>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>This building block is the reason why we perform all the other building blocks. In the end we want to get rid of the attacker and establish a clean base-line&lt;/li>
&lt;li>In this building block we need to implement a set of measures to achieve that&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The results from digital forensics (especially the extent of the attack) comes in very handy here&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Lessons Learned&lt;/strong> (usually not a working stream but something you do after the remediation)
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>After remediation is done and successful, it&amp;rsquo;s time to learn your lessons&lt;/li>
&lt;li>How can we avoid such incidents in the future?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>How can we improve our prevention, detection, and response?&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h1 id="the-role-of-incident-coordination">The Role of Incident Coordination
&lt;/h1>&lt;p>As an incident coordinator you are effectively leading the whole incident and it&amp;rsquo;s your responsibility the resolve the incident. Therefore a multitude of tasks must be performed in the coordination building block. These tasks involve&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Setting up and moderating regular status calls with all stakeholders&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Documenting and tracking status updates&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Assigning and tracking ongoing tasks&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Collecting results of all fulfilled tasks&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Ensuring critical decisions are made and documented&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Gathering and consolidating findings from all workstreams to maintain a situational overview&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Translating technical findings for management&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Communicating management decisions effectively to technical teams&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Ensuring all workstreams receive the necessary information&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Note that some of tasks can be delegated or supported by others, but responsibility ultimately falls back to you as an Incident Coordinator.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="why-incident-coordination-is-rare">Why Incident Coordination Is Rare
&lt;/h1>&lt;p>The reason why there are so many providers not able to offer incident coordination is because high-quality incident coordinators are very rare. The role requires a unique combination of skills:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Highly organized&lt;/strong>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Incidents are chaotic, especially in the beginning&lt;/li>
&lt;li>An Incident Coordinator must keep track of numerous moving parts&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Every little thing that gets overlooked might cause huge damage later on in the incident (e.g. you forgot to turn of one compromised system &amp;ndash;&amp;gt; Your containment was incomplete and the attacker persists)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>High-level view&lt;/strong>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>While forensic analysis like to get lost in technical details, someone needs to keep a high-level view of everything happening. This task goes to the incident coordinator&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Excellent communication skills&lt;/strong>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Since you have to communicate with forensic analysts as well as high-level management, you better work on your situational communication skills. Otherwise the analysts won&amp;rsquo;t respect you and management won&amp;rsquo;t understand you&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Your moderation skills should also be strong since you often have to moderated chaotic calls and it&amp;rsquo;s on you to direct everyone in a productive direction&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Sufficient technical know-how&lt;/strong>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>First of all you need sufficient know-how about how incidents, incident response, and cyber attacks work&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Next you need to know typical measures of containment, evidence acquisition, forensics and remediation&lt;/li>
&lt;li>To be able to communicate and direct the Digital Forensics block, you should have forensic experience yourself&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Incident Response Experience&lt;/strong>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>It takes years of hands-on Incident response experience until you are able to lead major incidents like APTs, Ransomware or Bad Insiders&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Ability to Stay Calm Under Pressure&lt;/strong>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>If the incident coordinator starts to panic, everybody is going to panic&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If you have all the skills described above, keeping calm shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be a problem :)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h1 id="conclusion">Conclusion
&lt;/h1>&lt;p>Now you know why Incident coordinators are rare. If you happen to find one, keep them and never let them go…&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you happen to be in the DACH region, we are training Incident Coordinators and Managers. So feel free to reach out.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>One final piece of advice: if you&amp;rsquo;re selecting an Incident Response provider, always ask how they manage and coordinate an incident. If they don’t have a clear answer, you’re usually dealing with a forensics provider, not a true Incident Response. If you are looking for a forensics provider, this is fine. If you are looking for an Incident Response provider, you should keep looking.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Cover Image by &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.freepik.com/free-photo/multi-colored-psychedelic-background_11761213.htm#from_element=detail_alsolike" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Freepik&lt;/a>&lt;/p>&lt;/blockquote></description></item></channel></rss>